Dug Falby

dug@goodlookslikethis.com 07549172692

Portfolio:

https://goodlookslikethis.com/cv/Dug Falby work.pdf

Profile:

I am a service design director with consulting experience developing new services in public sector environments and have specialised in UK public sector engagements since 2017. As a result, I have many contacts in service management and digital transformation in public sector and a deep understanding of the GSD service design model.

Most recently, I have been leading the design of a new service for HMRC using Al and natural language understanding (NLU) to help taxpayers make the most of the Coronavirus Job Retention Scheme.

In 2020, I have adapted to working remotely:

- I ran a test-and-learn program on a new service for an energy stakeholder (sponsored by Shell), allowing them to assess, pivot and iterate their proposition while maintaining BAU continuity.
- I helped the Scottish Government co-design remote learning with stakeholders and teachers
- I guided a policy consultation for Defra on how to reduce plastics pollution in the environment
- I redesigned the NHS breast screening service to leverage an agile approach

I am a believer in building skills in-house and have developed training programs for GSK and Lloyds to build their internal design capabilities.

I guide my customer's organisations safely through the intersections of data complexity, policy, cultural change, design thinking, customer experience, and digital transformation.

As a service designer, I always start with user needs, and am driven to understand the situations service users and providers find themselves in. I experience what isn't working for them, and explore their driving motivations.

I am currently BPSS cleared.

I'm hands-on and lead from the front. I'm equally happy working in a trusted advisor capacity or as a lead-practitioner.

Additionally, I have broad enterprise technology knowledge and an unusually wide breadth of experience growing multi-disciplinary teams. These include UX, strategy, creative and dev teams.

In 2016, I was named by BIMA as one the "Hot 100 people in digital" in the service design category.

Work experience

HMRC – Lead IxD (contract)

Dec 2020 – Present

I am currently guiding a team creating a conversational user interface for customer support at HMRC. The service will leverage artificial intelligence in utterance interpretation to provide a better customer experience for business taxpayers.

NHS – Lead Service Designer (contract)

Aug 2020 – Dec 2020

I guided a service design team using a data-centred approach to improve healthcare outcomes.

Education Scotland – Lead Service Designer (contract) May 2020 – Jul 2020 I led the discovery for an executive agency of the Scottish Government. The brief was to understand how to better influence teachers across the country to complete the right professional development programmes.

Foolproof – Service Design Director (contract)

Jan 2020 – Apr 2020

I led the discovery for a global energy brand needing to design and launch a new renewables business in Paris centred on the charging and servicing of electric vehicles.

Designit (Wipro Digital) – Design Director (contract)

May 2019 – Dec 2019

In this strategy and innovation role I was part of the recovery leadership team. My time was split between 50% solution-shaping with clients and 50% mentoring, inspiring, and doing hands-on design. In particular, I was tasked with stabilising the studio and rebuilding the experience design teams to meet the increased demand from the parent company pipeline with the primary challenge ensuring that a percentage of leads generated where suitably qualified.

Firetechcamps.com – Experience Designer

Feb 2019 – Apr 2019

I was contracted by Fire Tech, a service designed to help parents identify the right STEM courses for their children. I reviewed the design of the website search experience and produced new designs that delivered incremental sales uplift.

DfE – Lead Service Design Consultant

Jan 2019 – Feb 2019

Design consultant for the Department for Education. Worked in an agile discovery team for the "Get into teaching" programme. My role was to quickly uncover opportunities for digital channels and services to maximise the registration of new teachers in support of the primary marketing campaign.

Human Systems Ltd – Investor

Mar 2018 – Nov 2018

I led a discovery phase for "Insight Manager", a sense-making tool which uses AI and machine learning to support user research teams in leveraging maximum value from their research insights.

- Worked with both clients and practitioner colleagues to test it with user researchers
- Used co-design and mapping techniques to express complex issues with people, processes and technology
- Prototyped new service

DEFRA – Lead Service Design Consultant

Aug 2017 – Feb 2018

I led a team of five user researchers and interaction designers as part of Defra's "Livestock Information Programme". The programme had been running for a long time without design leadership and while much good discovery work had been performed, the project was not on track.

- Reorganised the team and optimised agile rituals and plan
- Worked with programme leadership to create a cross-silo roadmap
- Operationalised service design research by applying #JTBD methodology ensuring tangible outcomes from insight discovery
- Launched speculative design phase and tested low-fidelity prototypes with end users (farmers and livestock keepers)
- Guided product owner towards a realistic MVP
- Coded prototype of new service

HMRC – Lead Service Design Consultant

Jan 2017 – Aug 2017

I designed and lead a vision definition programme for my customer in the "Making Tax Digital" programme. Managed complex matrix of stakeholders resulting in successful delivery of programme vision for the new service.

- Primary research and speculative design
- As-is and to-be service blueprints
- Gap analysis and roadmap
- Vision canvas exercise with leadership to gain sponsorship

Create Future – Experience Design Consultant

July 2016 – Present

I am part of the Create Future associate network delivering strategic planning and consulting engagements with the Create Future team

Nile Service Design – Director of Consulting (Interim) Jan 2016 – May 2016 In this interim role I was accountable for increasing sales, framing the market relevance, creative health and profitability of Nile's service design, customer experience design and digital transformation consultancy business.

- Successfully delivered the new proposition
- Re-energised team and established agile design practises
- Created 'consultech' offer and sold it to Nile's two largest clients
- Created new website and social media pages
- Co-wrote the strategic roadmap with the strategy director
- Successfully handed over to leading principals

Career disruption event

Summer 2015

In 2015 my mother-in-law had a series of stroke events. To support my wife in her role as carer I left my role in London and moved North I have been contracting since then.

Accenture – Experience Director, Avanade Digital

Oct 2011 – Dec 2015

I was accountable for growing the user-centric digital transformation business at Avanade, an Accenture company. I built the practice up from 2 people in 2011 and used consultative selling techniques across the Accenture ecosystem to grow our sales.

- Guide customers in their adoption of digital across the enterprise
- Supervise strategy and UX teams. Ensure the UX teams are deployed efficiently and are happy in their daily activities
- Generated FY13 £2.5M in billings (includes £1.5M offshore billings) £5M in FY14
- Established digital consultancy as wedge offer for wider services business
- Supported £10M+ presales activity in FY14

Digital transformation projects include:

Diageo:

Redesign and transform the procurement ecosystem to change employee behaviour and reduce the cost blocked invoices in the system

Vodafone:

Redesign and transform customer billing to promote a channel shift from the Tier-1 callcentre to digital channels

Department of Social Protection (Irish Govt.):

Redesign and transform the way inspectors work to increase efficiency, reduce cost and improve return on investment in mobile technologies.

United Utilities:

Redesign and transform marketing/sales/service processes and infrastructure to reduce cost and improve customer satisfaction scores

Dixons Retail Plc – Head of Customer Experience

2010 - June 2011

I was accountable for multichannel ecommerce websites (currys.co.uk; pcworld.co.uk; Dixons.co.uk) reporting to the Group eCommerce Director.

I was the UX and customer experience leader on the DSGi transformation leadership team. I reported into David Walmsley and my work laid the foundation for the turnaround of Currys and PC World ecommerce websites.

Saved 450k on external agencies in Q12011 by building in-house teams required to rebuild and maintain ecommerce websites for the five Dixons chains.

Generated a continual month-on-month improvement of customer satisfaction index (ACSI) by implementing customer experience improvements.

Saved the business 150k/week in dropped baskets on previous design by performing user tests on shopping journey and optimising based on results.

Generated a 18% (estimated) uplift in sales by deploying algorithmically-driven merchandising (negotiated extremely advantageous contract with software partner).

Vodafone Ltd – Principal User Experience manager

2009 - 2010

In charge of concept generation lab focused on value creation and exchange. Based in the Vodafone Group Marketing directorate in Paddington.

Generated customer experience concepts and created service prototypes for revolutionary mobile marketplace. Secured 150k budget from Vodafone social investment fund to deploy pilot of mobile marketplace in Egypt and Romania Operating companies

Established and co-chaired cross-discipline working group between marketing, R&D and user experience functions

Ageas Protect (former Fortis Ltd) – User Experience Lead

2007 - 2008

Responsible for experience design of online life insurance product used by all UK IFA call centres. Accountable for integration of user-centred design methodology in SCRUM process environment.

Huge success in first year as a direct result of experience design:

- Which scored the product 9.5 out of 10, their highest rating ever
- Big efficiency gains. 60% immediate decisions, and 56% immediate accept. L&G, (nearest competitor), has a 53% immediate acceptance rate
- Year 1 customer satisfaction survey showed that 97.5% customer satisfaction
- Revamped product experience rated F&TRC "eee" excellence rating (top)

Orange/France Telecom Group – UX Consultant

2006 - 2007

Managed creation of communications, personalisation, personal cloud RIA products. Accountable for creation and maintenance of Group RIA design guidelines.

TMW Ltd – UX Consultant

2005 - 2006

Integrated agency. Accountable for digital concepting to support campaign creative. Responsible for pushing digital innovation across the agency. By end of contract Dug had enabled deep "think digital" culture across account and creative teams.

Space01 Ltd – UX Consultant

2004 - 2005

Integrated agency. Accountable for Friends Provident IFA financial services sites.

Niminim Ltd 2003 – 2004

Conceive http://www.lecturelist.org. Secure £100k NESTA funding. Launch service.

Bondworld / Pumpernickle.net Ltd

2000 - 2003

Games company. Built James Bond massively multiplayer role-playing game (MMRPG).

Bluewave Ltd 1999 – 2000

Digital agency. Accountable for Vision Group digital planning services.

OffWorld Industries Ltd

1996 - 1999

Digital agency. Accountable for design team delivery.

Education

Art Student's League, New York Columbia University, New York Lycée De Sèvres

One year Fine Arts course BA History of Art, Columbia College Economics Baccalaureate

<u>Mobility / languages</u> UK passport. Will travel. Native French/English speaker. Conversational Italian.